Today's דף daf is כ"ו, Chaf Vav, 26. We are finally going
to transition into the שופר shofar part of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
of this מסכת. masechet. We just wrap up issues of קידוש החודש
Kiddush Hachodesh and we pick up on the bottom of כ"ה עמוד
ב'. Chaf Hey Amud Bet. It's about ten lines from the bottom,
four-five lines before the lines get wide. ראוהו בית דין שנים ויעידו
בשניהם. Rauhu Beit Din shnayim veyaidu bishneihem. So the משנה mishna assumes
that if the בית דין Beit Din sees it, they still need
to go for the formal process of testifying and discusses, you know,
breaking off and having some people testify. The גמרא Gemara doesn't understand
why this is true because the גמרא Gemara will introduce the principle
of לא תהא שמיעה גדולה מראיה, lo tehei shemiah gedolah mereiyah, that
hearing it should not be better than seeing it, so why would
you need to testify if you saw it yourself? So that's now
the issue the גמרא Gemara puts its attention to. Let's take a
look. ואמאי, Ve'amai, here you go, לא תהא שמיעה גדולה מראיה, lo
tehei shemiah gedolah mereiyah, why do you have to have people break
off and testify? Hearing it from witnesses should not be better than
seeing it yourself. Again, the משנה mishna assumes no, you need to
go through a formal process, but okay. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav
Zeira, כגון שראוהו בלילה. kigon sherauhu balaila. They saw it at night,
and since as we've been emphasizing before that you can only do
this process in the day, you could only accept the witnesses in
the day and even if you accepted the witnesses in the day
you can only say מקודש מקודש Mekudash Mekudash in the day, so
if they saw it at night, their act of seeing does not
count like an act of receiving testimony. Now notice by the way
the response would be who cares, they still know. So the next
morning I know, I saw it, why do I need to hear
testimony? So the גמרא Gemara does not go so far even in
this line of לא תהא שמיעה גדולה מראיה lo tehei shemiah gedolah
mereiyah to say that knowing avoids the need of a formal process.
All it is suggesting is the act of seeing should count as
an equivalent formal process, but it's still an act of seeing that
counts instead of an act of hearing testimony. So the same way
the hearing of testimony must be in the day, the act of
seeing must be in the day. So the גמרא Gemara is not
being so radical to say who needs witnesses, you know, you saw
it yourself. No,
seeing counts as hearing witnesses. And therefore if the same way you
don't hear witnesses at night, the seeing at night doesn't register, you
have to wait till the next morning and then the next morning
you need a formal process, so you have to now accept the
witnesses the next morning. Okay, the idea they saw it at night
is of course completely understandable because the new moon is visible at
night, not in the day, right? The sun sets and then you
see the new moon. So the seeing didn't count, they have to
wait till the next morning and then they have to hear the
witnesses. Okay. ראוהו שלשה והן בית דין יעמדו שנים ויושיבו מחבריהם אצל
היחיד. Rauhu shlosha vehen Beit Din yaamdu shnayim veyoshivu mechavreihem eitzel hayachid.
If three people saw and you can't just have two break off
because you don't have enough left, then you have to have two
break off and you have to replace them with two other people
to now serve on the בית דין. Beit Din. אמאי הכא נמי
נימא לא תהא שמיעה גדולה מראיה. Amai hacha nami nima lo tehei
shemiah gedolah mereiyah. Same question, why do you need a formal testifying?
Just the seeing should count as the same process. וכי תימא הכא
נמי כגון שראוהו בלילה, Vechi teima hacha nami kigon sherauhu balaila, you'll
give me the same answer: they saw it at night. Same story.
And therefore you gotta do this the next morning and therefore you
need to accept witnesses. No. היינו הך. Haynu hach. So why do
you need the second case? It's telling me the same thing as
the first case. הגמרא Gemara says no. סיפא איצטריכא ליה. Sefa itztricha
lei. No, there's a new point added in the end: דאין היחיד
נאמן על ידי עצמו, de'ein hayachid ne'eman al yedei atzmo, that one
person is not, again this funny phrase believed, but one person can't
serve as a בית דין. Beit Din. דסלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל ותניא,
Desalka daitach amina ho'il vetanya, I would have thought since we teach
דיני ממונות בשלושה dinei mamonot bishlosha that you normally judge monetary cases
with three, ואם היה מומחה לרבים דן אפילו ביחיד, ve'im hayah mumcheh
lerabbim dan afilu beyachid, and if the guy has authority and is
an expert and is acknowledged for the masses, whatever מומחה mumcheh means
we'll talk about it when we do סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, anyway even an
individual person can sometimes be a judge. הכא נמי נקדשיה ביחיד, Hacha
nami nekadshei beyachid,
maybe here also you could do it as an individual judge. קא
משמע לן Kamashma lan that you can't. Okay, so that's the חידוש.
chiddush. The חידוש chiddush in the end is that you can't have
one person as a judge,
not about שמיעה shemiah and ראיה. reiyah. ואימא הכא נמי, Ve'aima hacha
nami, take that's a good argument: if one person is a judge
for, biblically, for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, why shouldn't he count as
a judge for the new moon? No. אין לך מומחה לרבים בישראל
יותר ממשה. Ein lecha mumcheh lerabbim beYisrael yoter miMoshe.
No, because nobody is a greater expert and authority over the Jewish
people than משה. Moshe. וקאמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא עד דאיכא אהרן
בהדך, Veka'amar lei Hakadosh Baruch Hu ad de'ika Aharon bahadach, and God
says you need to have אהרן Aharon with you, דכתיב ויאמר ה'
אל משה ואל אהרן בארץ מצרים לאמר החודש הזה לכם. dechtiv Vayomer
Hashem el Moshe ve'el Aharon be'eretz Mitzrayim lemor Hachodesh hazeh lachem. Okay,
of course a little bit of a problem is that אהרן Aharon
and משה Moshe are brothers, so they're פסול כדיינים, pasul kidayanim, but
okay as a model that you need a בית דין Beit Din
you can't do it by yourself. Okay, and again the obvious reason
would be that here the בית דין Beit Din is not just
to sit judgment but to represent the Jewish people, so you need
actually a, you know, at least a larger group than one to
be a representative of the entire people. Okay, but the basic point
is: why do you need to accept testimony? Because seeing counts as
a formal process of accepting testimony, but that can only be in
the day and this was at night. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says לאימור דעד נעשה דיין. le'eimor de'eid na'aseh dayan. Now this משנה
mishna says that an עד, eid, not somebody who... That after he
testified could be a judge, because that would mean that you wouldn't
need to bring other people. You'd stand in front of the one
guy, you'd say here's my testimony, and then you'd turn around and
say okay, good testimony. That would be one example of עד נעשה
דיין. eid na'aseh dayan. That's what תוספות Tosafot calls עד המעיד נעשה
דיין. eid hameid na'aseh dayan. That's an extreme case. We might say
that by certain cases of דיני ממונות dinei mamonot or whatever. But
here, we're not talking about עד המעיד, eid hameid, we're talking about
עד שראה. eid sherah. The fact that you, I am the דיין,
dayan, you Charlie, you were part of my בית דין, beit din,
you went and you testified, I'm listening to your testimony, but I
also saw it myself. So maybe that makes me partial. And since
I have the ability to be an עד, eid, I cannot, that
disqualifies me from serving as the דיין. dayan. So that's the question.
Somebody who had the possibility of being an עד eid now is
serving as a דיין. dayan. Is that really true? לימא מתניתין דלא
כרבי עקיבא, leima matnitin d'lo ke-Rabbi Akiva, let's say it's not like
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, baraita,
סנהדרין
שראו אחד שהרג את הנפש, Sanhedrin sherah echad she-harag et hanefesh, a
סנהדרין Sanhedrin that saw, meaning at least a group of twenty-three, which
you need for capital crime, somebody who committed murder. Top of דף
כ"ו עמוד א', daf chaf-vav amud aleph, מקצתם נעשו עדים ומקצתם נעשו
דיינים, דברי רבי טרפון. miktzatam na'asu eidim umiktzatam na'asu dayanim, divrei Rabbi
Tarfon. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says fine, let some of them serve
as witnesses, and the others, we'll have other people join them and
they'll be the judges plus other people. So even though you saw,
you can still serve as a judge. You didn't testify, somebody else
will testify, but you, it doesn't disqualify you from serving as a
judge.
רבי עקיבא אומר כולם נעשו עדים ואין עד נעשה דיין. Rabbi Akiva
omer kulam na'asu eidim ve-ein eid na'aseh dayan. If you want, if
you saw it, you are disqualified from being a judge. So isn't
our משנה mishna not רבי עקיבא'ס? Rabbi Akiva's? גמרא Gemara says no,
אפילו תימא רבי עקיבא, afilu teima Rabbi Akiva, even רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי עקיבא התם אלא בדיני נפשות, דרחמנא
אמר ושפטו העדה והצילו העדה. ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Akiva hatam
ela b'dinei nefashot, d'rachmana amar v'shaftu ha-eda v'hitzilu ha-eda. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says you cannot be a judge in a in a in
a capital crime because then you are already biased based on what
you saw. And by the way, as we know, you know, I
don't know if they didn't know this before, you know, in the
past they used to think that eyewitness testimony is the most reliable.
You know, now of course they know that eyewitness testimony is highly
unreliable. So anyway, but even if you ignore the unreliability of it,
you know, the whole issue that they have about like showing pictures
to the jury and that the graphic nature of the pictures will,
you know, will taint them and will, you know, will sort of
like lead to so that they won't be able to sort of
judge it rationally and clearly because their emotion, emotional reaction to actually
witnessing it, you know, will have an influence. So that's sort of
what's saying, you know, if you saw it yourself, you've got too
many things that are might be influencing your ability to judge this
impartially with a certain sense of a detached distance. So that's why
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if you actually saw it, you cannot
serve as a judge. So עד כאן
לא קאמר רבי עקיבא התם אלא בדיני נפשות, דרחמנא אמר ושפטו העדה,
ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Akiva hatam ela b'dinei nefashot, d'rachmana amar
v'shaftu ha-eda, they'll judge the congregation, והצילו העדה, v'hitzilu ha-eda, they have
to try to save the innocent people. You need a certain amount
of dispassionate distance. וכיון דחזיוהו דקטל נפשא לא מצי חזו ליה זכותא,
ve-keivan d'chazei'uhu d'katal nafsha lo matzu chazu lei zechuta, and if you
saw this guy commit murder,
you'll be so biased you won't try to argue in his defense,
you won't try to think about extenuating circumstances and maybe you didn't
exactly see it, you know, or maybe you misunderstood something. In your
mind, emotionally what registered is this guy's a murderer and I saw
it and I saw it. So therefore you're disqualified. אבל הכא אפילו
רבי עקיבא מודה, aval hacha afilu Rabbi Akiva modei, but here for
something like קידוש החודש, kiddush hachodesh, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would not
say that seeing the new moon disqualifies you from hearing witnesses testify
to the new moon. Okay, so there are three cases. By דיני
נפשות, dinei nefashot, you cannot even if you look at תוספות, Tosafot,
nice little summary at the end of תוספות דרחמנא אמר, Tosafot d'rachmana
amar, תוספות Tosafot says the following. He says like this. ובעד, u-be-eid,
it's about six five lines before תוספות'ס Tosafot's ends, the line starting
with the word ובעד. u-be-eid. ובעד נעשה דיין יש שינויים חלוקים כמו
שפירשנו פרק ב' דכתובות. u-be-eid na'aseh dayan yesh shinnuyim challukim kemo she-perashnu
perek bet d'ketuvot. דבעדות החודש דאורייתא, עד הרואה הוא דנעשה דיין. d'be-iddut
hachodesh de-oraita, eid haroeh hu d'na'aseh dayan. That in עדות החודש, iddut
hachodesh, if you saw you can still be a judge, you're not
disqualified. ובקיום שטרות דרבנן, אפילו עד המעיד נעשה דיין, u-be-kiyum shetarot derabbanan,
afilu eid hameid na'aseh dayan, when it comes to validating the signatures
on documents which is only
Rabbinic, even you could testify and then turn around and be the
judge. Okay, so that's the opposite שיטה. sheetah. ובדיני נפשות, u-be-dinei nefashot,
and as we saw, in capital crimes אפילו עד הרואה אינו נעשה
דיין. afilu eid haroeh eino na'aseh dayan. Even just seeing it disqualifies
you. Okay, so in an extreme case, קיום שטרות, kiyum shetarot, you
can testify and then be the דיין. dayan. In most cases in
the middle, if you see you are not disqualified, but you can't
play both roles. And in דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, the very fact
that you saw it disqualifies you. Yes.
You're referring to דיני נפשות dinei nefashot as capital cases, but there
are cases that are not capital cases where the penalty would be
lashes rather than death.
So where does that fall into? Okay, so that's a good question.
Right, I mean תוספות Tosafot has extremes, right? What do you do
about normal דיני ממונות dinei mamonot or whatever? Okay, so let's, yeah,
we'll just leave that as a good question for now.
Yeah. It's interesting that the biblical word that we translate as congregation
is really the group, collective group of witnesses, right, the עדה. edah.
Oh, the עדה. edah.
No, I don't want to get into that. That has to do
with the sense that in the פסוקים pesukim? *psukim*, you know, the
פסוקים psukim. *psukim*, it has that the witnesses throw the stones and
whatever, and there's a sense like the whole community is judging through
the court system. Right, right. Yeah, but it's not okay, but it
is the congregation, it's just the congregation as all active participants in
the judgment through the various, what
is it, judicial official terminology that is used to describe the congregation
of the people. Yeah, interesting.
Yeah. Okay, let's now transition to finally the part of this מסכת
masechet, *masechet* that deals with ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, starting
with the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of שופר Shofar, *shofar*. Okay, כל השופרות
כשרים *kol hashofarot ksheirim*, all horns are good for a שופר shofar?
*shofar*, חוץ משל פרה chutz mishel parah, *chutz mishal parah*, except for
that of a cow, מפני שהוא קרן mipnei shehu keren. *mipnei shehu
keren*, because it's a קרן keren, *keren*. What does that mean? We'll
unpack that. אמר רבי amar Rabbi, יוסי *Amar Rabbi Yosi*, says Rabbi
Yosi, והלא כל השופרות נקראו קרן keren. *valo kol hashofarot nikru keren*?
You can't say because it's called a קרן keren. *keren*, because all
שופרות shofaros *shofarot* are called a קרן keren, *keren*. How do you
know that? דכתיב De'chtiv, *dichtiv* שנאמר *shene'emar*, the verse says, במשוך בקרן
היובל המה יעלו בהר *bimshoch
bkeren hayovel heimah ya'alu bahar*. When you draw out, extend the קרן
keren *keren*, the horn of the יובל Yovel, *yovel*, and a יובל
yovel *yovel* is a ram as we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So therefore a ram's horn, it's also called a שופר shofar?
*shofar* because, I'm sorry, that's not a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* by הר
סיני *Har Sinai*, that's a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* by יהושע *Yehoshua*. But
it says במשוך בקרן היובל *bimshoch bkeren hayovel*, this actually talks about
the falling of the walls of יריחו *Yericho*, excuse me. So it
says במשוך בקרן היובל *bimshoch bkeren hayovel*, the end of the פסוק
*pasuk* is בשמעכם את קול השופר *b'shom'achem et kol hashofar*. Okay, and
then יריעו כל העם תרועה *yari'u kol ha'am tru'ah* etc., and the
walls will fall. Okay, so anyway there we're talking about a ram's
horn because as we know from הר סיני *Har Sinai*, the יובל
yovel. *yovel* is a שופר shofar. *shofar* and it's called here a
קרן keren *keren*. So even a ram's horn is called a קרן
keren *keren*, so why do you make a פרה parah *parah*, a
cow's horn any different? Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. שפיר אמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Shafir amar Rabbi Yosi*, Rabbi
Yosi makes a good point, even the ram's horn is called a
קרן keren. *keren*. ורבנן *Verabbanan*, the Rabbis would say back, כל השופרות
אקרו קרן keren ואקרו שופר shofar? *kol hashofarot ikru keren ve'ikru shofar*,
all other horns are called both a שופר shofar *shofar* and a
קרן keren *keren*. Now where do you know other horns are called
a שופר shofar. *shofar*? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say, but רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* points us to הר סיני *Har Sinai* where it says
במשוך היובל המה יעלו בהר *bimshoch hayovel heimah ya'alu bahar*, right, not
במשוך בקרן היובל *bimshoch bkeren hayovel* but במשוך היובל *bimshoch hayovel*, and
then the פסוק *pasuk* says ויהי קול השופר הולך וחזק מאוד *vayehi
kol hashofar holech vechazek me'od*. So there the יובל yovel *yovel*, which
we are taking for granted means a ram's horn, is called a
שופר shofar, *shofar*. So other horns are called a שופר shofar *shofar*
and are called a קרן keren. *keren*. דפרה קרן keren. אקרי שופר
shofar לא אקרי *deparah keren ikri shofar lo ikri*, but the cow's
horn, it's only called a קרן keren, *keren*, not called a שופר
shofar *shofar*. דכתיב *dichtiv* שנאמר *shene'emar*, the verse says, בכור שורו הדר
לו וקרני ראם re'eim? קרניו *bechor shoro hadar lo vekarnei re'eim karnav*.
The firstborn of the ox is a glory to him and the
horns of a ראם *re'eim*, which is which is normally which is
translated as, what's a ראם *re'eim*?
Fierce wild ox?
Wild ox is a ראם *re'eim*. I've often seen other ones like
a I don't know, I know other animals identified as ראם *re'eim*.
Anyway, its horns. Okay, so anyway you have horn associated with ox
or cow, and you do not have the word שופר shofar, *shofar*
associated with it, so because it's never called a שופר shofar *shofar*
it's invalid. So the I'm going to read this a little and
then I'm going to tell you the רמב"ן's Ramban, *Ramban's* understanding of
this, which puts, makes a little bit more sense of this. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi אמר לך *Rabbi Yosi amar lach*, Rabbi Yosi will
say to you, דפרה נמי אקרי שופר shofar *deparah nami ikri shofar*,
what are you talking about? A cow's horn is also called a
שופר shofar *shofar*. דכתיב *dichtiv* שנאמר *shene'emar*, ותיטב לה' משור פר par.
*vetitiv la'Hashem mishor par*, it will be my offering will be more
desirous to God than a שור shor, פר *shor par*. So, not
cow, an ox bull. Okay, do we use the word ox and
bull any different? Bull-ox. Yeah, a bull-ox. But anyway but the bull
or ox refers to, anyway in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* a פר
*par* refers to a one only after it's like three days old,
and a שור *shor* is even when it's just born. No, that
would be פרה parah *parah*. So I don't know, but I'm saying
in English, do the word ox and bull mean something different?
They're two different animals. They are?
No, I thought they're both male cows.
I thought an ox was a bovine.
All right, I don't know. Anyway, okay, משור פר *mishor par*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אם שור למה פר *im shor lama
par*? If it's a שור *shor*, which is again when it is
young, even young it's called a שור *shor*, why are you calling
it a פר *par*? ואם פר *ve'im par*, and if it's from
an older cow,
bull, למה שור *lama shor*? Why are you calling it a שור
*shor*? אלא מאי שור פר *ela mai shor par*? What does שור
פר *shor par* mean? משופר *mi-shofar*! Ah, so שור פר *shor par*,
שופר shofar *shofar*! So therefore you see that an ox's horn is
also called a שופר shofar *shofar*. So I just gotta tell you,
this like reminds me, שור פר *shor par*, שור פר *shor par*,
שופר shofar *shofar*! So anyway, so his cousin said that once like
20, 30 years ago, he saw this movie in Israel which had
like subtitles, it was an American movie. So in the English, they
were like, you know, they were bringing out like soup and rice
for dinner and the title said soup, rice, soup, rice, surprise. So
then he said, he said the subtitles read מרק, אורז, מרק, אורז,
הפתעה *marak, orez, marak, orez, haftah*.
Anyway, there you go. Okay, anyway, שופר shofar. שופר, shofar. there you
go.
So he says an ox is simply any bovine that is trained
to be a work animal.
Ah, as opposed to a bull, which is just a male cow
but it's not trained that way.
Right, and in fact most oxen are actually castrated males.
Ah, okay.
Because a bull is a non-castrate.
Castrated doesn't make it a different species, just makes it a castrate.
Yes, but it's still, I would say, significant.
Yes, okay. Anyway, okay. So now we're going to say right, so
the גמרא Gemara says, רבנן, Rabbanan, so what would the Rabbis say
back? כרב מתנא, Ke-Rav Masna, they'd say back like רב מתנא, Rav
Masna, דאמר רב מתנא בר שור פר שהוא גדול כפר d'amar Rav
Masna bar shor par she-hu gadol ke-par
that it was a one-day-old, again this is getting back to things
that at the time of creation were created fully developed. So even
when it was a שור, one day old, it was as big
as a פר. Okay, but now we're basically saying the whole debate
is: is a cow's horn ever called a שופר? shofar.
The רבנן Rabbanan who go by this thing of רבי יוסי הגלילי?
Rabbi Yose HaGalili? Exactly. Okay, so now obviously this is not totally
satisfying. In the end we're having these tiny little debates about is
do we ever find that a ram's horn, that a cow's horn
is called a שופר? shofar. Everything is called a קרן, keren it's
also called a שופר. shofar. Is this called a שופר? shofar, So
the גמרא Gemara tries other answers. So עולא אמר היינו טעמא דרבנן.
Ulla amar hainu ta'ama de-Rabbanan. Let me tell you the real reason
of the Rabbis that says that they don't want a cow's horn.
כרב חסדא, Ke-Rav Chisda, like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, דאמר רב חסדא
מפני מה אין כהן גדול נכנס בבגדי זהב לפני ולפנים? d'amar Rav
Chisda mipnei mah ein kohen gadol nichnas bi-vigdei zahav lifnai ve-lifnim? Why
on Yom Kippur does the כהן גדול kohen gadol not wear his
gold garments, vestments into the Holy of Holies when he does the
עבודת פנים, avodas pnim, לעבוד עבודה, la'avod avoda, to do the service?
לפי שאין קטיגור נעשה סניגור, lefi she-ein kategore na'aseh sanegore, because the
prosecuting attorney cannot turn around and become the defense attorney. Gold is
the prosecuting attorney. It evokes the חטא העגל chet ha-egel and therefore
it cannot be used to in this in the עבודה. avoda. Okay,
so and the שופר shofar is also from the cow, so it
evokes חטא העגל, chet ha-egel, you're not going to use it.
Now that's
a great word, קטיגור kategore and סניגור. sanegore. Okay, thank you. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to obviously point out some of
the problems with this argument, both internally and as a parallel to
the שופר. shofar. Let's take a look. ולא, ve-lo, really? You can't
have that? You can't have anything related to cows in the עבודת
פנים? avodas pnim? והאיכא דם פר, ve-ha-ika dam par, how about the
blood of the ox that's brought in in the עבודת פנים avodas
pnim on Yom Kippur? גמרא Gemara says: No, הוה אשתני אשתני, hava
ishtani ishtani, it doesn't look like a cow anymore. Okay, it's blood,
so that's not as evocative. But so גמרא Gemara says: והאיכא ארון
וכפורת וכרוב, ve-ha-ika aron ve-kapores ve-cherub,
how about all the other things that are gold inside of the
קודש קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim? The ארון aron and the cover and the
cherubs?
חוטא בל יקריב chotei bal yakriv ka'amrinan,
the sinner cannot use things that evoke the sin, the gold or
whatever or the שופר, shofar you cannot use the things that are
evoking the sin, you're the sinner approaching God.
These things are just part of the furniture. You're not using them
and bringing them in and approaching God with them. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says: והאיכא כף ומחתה, ve-ha-ika kaf u-machtah, but Aaron brings in
the fire pan and the, you know, and the pan that carries
the incense. Aaron the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, that's gold. חוטא בל
יתנאה chotei bal yisna'eh ka'amrinan. No, the problem is as a sinner
you cannot use these things to make yourself like, to you know,
look nice and to beautify yourself with. Whereas these, they're just vessels.
Again, I don't know exactly the difference, but clothing is very different.
Again, how that relates to שופר shofar is not clear, but clothing,
I would say, a little different than יתנאה, yisna'eh, clothing identifies you,
like clothing is part of your identity, right? You put it on
your body, it becomes integrated into who you are. So therefore you
don't want that close to be attaching your identity to something that
evokes the sin as opposed to just using the vessels. Now of
course you'll say the שופר shofar also is a type of a
vessel. Right, so you know, רש"י Rashi also says, okay, but you're
somehow glorifying yourself, it makes beautiful music, so somehow it
more connects you to it than just using it as an inanimate
vessel. Okay, but you're seeing already the weakness of the of the
whole parallel. Okay. גמרא Gemara says: והאיכא בגדי זהב מבחוץ? ve-ha-ika bigdei
zahav mi-bachutz? How about the, you know, what you wear when you
do the other עבודות avodas and the, you know, the gold vestments
that you wear outside of the
קודש קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim? So גמרא Gemara says: מפנים mi-pnim ka'amrinan. Okay,
it's only a problem to do it in the innermost sanctum. So
גמרא Gemara says: שופר נמי מבחוץ הוא? shofar nami mi-bachutz hu? The
שופר shofar. isn't in the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, it's outside. גמרא
Gemara says: כיון דלזכרון הוא כפנים דמי. kevan de-le-zikaron hu ke-pnim dami.
No, because the שופר, shofar, this is like a great Rosh Hashanah
sermon, you know, the שופר shofar it pierces right on, you know,
right through all the heavens, right into God's innermost sanctum, it comes
up to raise our memory before God, so it's bringing us in
direct encounter with God and that's like לפני ולפנים. lifnai ve-lifnim. Okay,
very powerful statement. And therefore it can't be out of a cow.
The גמרא Gemara says,
והתניא מפני שקרן קרויה? Vehatanya mipnei shekeren keruyah? So how could you
say that it's this whole thing about cows and עגל? eigel? The
משנה Mishnah says קרן. keren, That's the problem. So the גמרא Gemara,
says חדא ועוד קאמר. chada veod kaamar. Yeah, that and something else.
חדא chada number one or something else and that. Number one, חדא,
chada, the first point, the real point is דאין קטיגור נעשה סניגור,
dein kategur naaseh sanigur, that you can't use things from the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah חטא העגל. cheit haeigel. ועוד, veod, and another thing
which is not my real argument, I'll just throw it in, מפני
שהוא קרן. mipnei shehu keren. It's a קרן. רבי Rabbi, יוסי will
say back, וקאמרת דאין קטיגור נעשה סניגור, vekaamarta dein kategur naaseh sanigur,
your whole issue about using things that evoke חטא העגל, cheit haeigel,
הני מילי מבפנים, hani mili mibifnim, I don't buy your whole argument
that that that that שופר shofar
is like the is like the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. That's only
in the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. שופר מבחוץ הוא, shofar mibachutz hu,
the שופר shofar is outside. וקאמרת מפני שהוא קרן, vekaamarta mipnei shehu
keren, and your argument that it's all כל שופר נמי איקרי קרן,
kol shofar nami ikri keren, all even even a ram's horn is
called a קרן, so that's not an argument. But notice what the
גמרא Gemara, did, it's interesting it introduced another argument that maybe the
other argument is primary because the גמרא Gemara really recognizes the weakness
of this whole קרן argument and therefore in an astounding way, it's
not like it's got a קשיא kashya and a contradiction, I mean
this is really astounding like the אמוראים Amoraim are just bothered, like
what type of argument is this, קרן or whatever, so they invent
new arguments and they try to say that the whole argument of
קרן in the משנה Mishnah is a secondary one. So we're not
done, this is one thing of קטיגור סניגור, kategur sanigur, now we're
going to give another thing. Let's take a look. אביי אמר, Abaye
amar, אביי Abaye says, היי טעמא דרבנן, hai taama derabbanan, this is
the reason of the רבנן, Rabbanan, שופר אמר רחמנא ולא שנים ושלשה
שופרות. shofar amar rachmana velo shnayim ushloshah shofaros. It says a שופר
shofar and it only says שופר shofar by the way explicitly by
יובל, Yovel, not by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and not two or
three שופרות shofaros. and we're going to learn later that you can't
stick one שופר shofar, into another one and blow. והאי פרה, vehai
parah, and the one of the cow, כיון דקאי גלדי גלדי, keivan
dekaei gildei gildei, since it's basically in
in layers, מחזי כשנים ושלשה שופרות. michzei keshnayim ushloshah shofaros. It looks
like two or three. So now, hey, guess what guys, we make
a שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, we can erase the pictures of the moon.
Okay, so there's that. So for anyway, but apparently
a cow's horn looks something like, you know, it looks like there're
segments, you know, each thing that grows new each year. Okay, so
that looks like two or three שופרות. shofrot And therefore that's why
it's not good. So the גמרא Gemara. says, והתניא
מפני שהוא קרן קאמר, vehatanya mipnei shehu keren kaamar, but the תניא
tanya says that the problem is because it's called a קרן. So
the גמרא Gemara says, חדא ועוד קאמר. chada veod kaamar.
No,
that one thing and that also. חדא דשופר אחד אמר רחמנא ולא
שנים ושלשה שופרות. chada deshofar echad amar rachmana velo shnayim ushloshah shofaros.
The real thing is it can't be two or three and this
looks like two or three. ועוד, veod, and the other thing, מפני
שהוא קרן. mipnei shehu keren. רבי יוסי אמר לחבריה, Rabbi Yosi amar
lachavreih, רבי יוסי would say back to you, דקאמרת שופר אחד אמר
רחמנא ולא שנים ושלשה שופרות, dekaamarta shofar echad amar rachmana velo shnayim
ushloshah shofaros, כיון דמחובר אהדדי, keivan demichubar ahadadi, since it's all connected,
it's not really two different things. חד הוא, chad hu, it's one.
ודקאמרת מפני שהוא קרן, vedekaamarta mipnei shehu keren, the other thing it's
a horn, כל שופר נמי איקרי קרן. kol shofar nami ikri keren.
Okay, they're all called a horn. Now, it's as I said, fascinating
that the גמרא, Gemara you know, is like can't relate to the
power of the point of the רבנן Rabbanan and is making up
new arguments. Okay, and clearly, right, there's some, so you know, there's
they can't understand exactly the significance of do you find that it's
called a קרן or not find that it's called a קרן and
so on. So what's really going on here? So רמב"ן, Ramban you
should be aware and this will be relevant for the rest of
the מסכת, רמב"ן Ramban has a famous דרשה לראש השנה, drasha leRosh
Hashanah, which it's really like, I can tell you,
I unless you're a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, I pity the people
that had to be in the שול shul when he gave his
דרשה לראש השנה drasha leRosh Hashanah because basically, it's his commentary to
מסכת ראש השנה Masechet Rosh Hashanah from this point on, basically, topic
by topic, where not like line by line, but he basically and
discusses every single topic that arises within the issues of הלכות שופר
hilchos shofar and הלכות תפילה hilchos tfillah on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah.
and goes through everything. It's a great פירוש peirush on מסכת ראש
השנה. Masechet Rosh Hashanah. I don't know exactly about giving it in
שול shul for your דרשה. drasha. At the very end of like
what must be a hundred pages, he has one paragraph that's מוסר.
mussar. Okay, a basic paragraph, it's good מוסר. mussar. His basic מוסר
mussar is he says look, if you didn't have the opportunity to
do תשובה, teshuvah, you would sin once and then you'd be punished
for your sin. Now that God's given you the opportunity to do
תשובה, teshuvah, every minute you're not doing תשובה, teshuvah, you're essentially repeating
your sin. So you'd better do תשובה. teshuvah. That was his מוסר.
mussar. The rest of the time was spent in a hundred pages
of a commentary on on topics of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah So
one of the first things he deals with is this issue about
קרן. And he says what's going on here, איקרי קרן לא איקרי
קרן ikri keren lo ikri keren and he says, actually he says,
if you look at the משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah doesn't say
the problem with a פרה is that it's called a קרן. The
משנה Mishnah says the problem with a פרה is מפני שהוא קרן.
mipne shehu keren, And the רמב"ן Ramban says that קרן, what is
the real difference? A cow's horn doesn't have marrow. It's all bone.
bone. You have to carve out the bone to make it into
a horn, whereas a ram's horn has marrow and you just essentially
scoop out the marrow. And therefore he says, a cow's horn to
be a musical instrument is essentially manufactured, right, as opposed to a
other animal where you scoop out the marrow, that's essentially a natural
שופר. shofar So he says the difference isn't what it's called, the
difference is is that a type of a thing that you have
to basically create as a manufactured musical instrument, which is what קרן
means, there is that is invalid because it is essentially different than
something that is naturally can be used as a שופר. shofar So
now how that fits into the גמרא, Gemara. why does the גמרא
Gemara bother with the פסוקים? psukim So he tries to make it
fit into the גמרא. Gemara But putting the גמרא Gemara aside, it's
a great פשט pshat in the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna says
מפני שהוא קרן, mipne shehu keren, not מפני שנקרא קרן. mipne shenikra
keren.
Okay, and by the way, somebody said to him afterwards, this is
just so wonderful because it's like, it's just so real to life.
Somebody said to him, oh תוספות Tosfos already said that חדוש. chidush.
He says, what do you mean תוספות Tosfos said that חדוש? chidush?
So if you look at תוספות, Tosfos, right, it says חוץ משל
mashal. פרה, תוספות Tosfos says הא דלא קתני נמי חוץ משל ראם
דראם נמי אקרי קרן דכתיב וקרני ראם קרניו וכתיב ומקרני רמים עניתני.
ha d'lo katani nami chutz mishel re'eim d're'eim nami itkrei keren d'chtiv
v'karnei re'eim karnav v'chtiv u-mikarnei re'eim anitani. Why didn't it also exclude
ראם? So תוספות Tosfos says ושמא אינם חלולים, v'shema einam chalulim, maybe
they're not naturally hollow ואינם ראויים לשופר, v'einam re'uyim l'shofar, and they're
not fit for being
a שופר. shofar
So you see תוספות Tosfos says because it's not naturally hollow it
can't be a שופר. shofar הרמב"ן HaRamban points out, first of all,
if תוספות Tosfos said it, then wonderful, and I was מכוון mechaven
to תוספות Tosfos and that's wonderful. But by the way, תוספות Tosfos
isn't saying it. תוספות Tosfos says that we didn't bother excluding them
because
they're not usually used for a שופר. shofar He didn't say that's
the reason that it's being invalidated. The משנה mishna says the reason
it's invalidated is for that reason. תוספות Tosfos just saying it wasn't
relevant to discuss another case because those things are not used. So
anyway תוספות Tosfos though does recognize the difference of the physical difference
between a cow's horn and another type of a horn, but the
רמב"ן says that's actually what the משנה mishna means, מפני שהוא קרן,
not מפני שנקרא קרן. mipne shenikra keren. You had a question? No,
okay, all right fine. So now the גמרא Gemara. back to the
גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara, says מאי משמע, mai mashma, three
lines down in the middle sized line. מאי משמע דהאי
יובלא לישנא דדיכרא הוא,
mai mashma d'hai
yovla lishna d'dichra hu, why what makes you where do you get
the idea that יובל Yovel means a ram's horn? Because that's been
our assumption and whether it's called שופר, shofar called קרן, but we
understand it means a ram's horn. דתניא, d'tanya, we saw in a
ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi Akiva, כשהלכתי לערביא, k'she-halachti l'Arvaya,
when I went to Arabia, היו קורין לדיכרא יובלא, hayu korin l'dichra
yovla, they would call a ram a יובל. Yovel And that's important,
now we understand that when the תורה Torah says יובל Yovel, it
means a ram's horn. Now we're going to get into a little
passage about how you can learn sometimes hard difficult words from the
vernacular, you know sort of like scholars right if they're trying to
reconstruct what words meant, ancient Semitic languages, they'll also like look at
how certain words are used in the vernacular today in Arabic and
so on and try, so how the people are using the words
can often be a good evidence in terms of what those words
originally meant. So now we're going to actually tap some examples of
that. ואמר רבי עקיבא, v'amar Rabbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
said, כשהלכתי לגליא, k'she-halachti l'Galya, when I went to where is that?
Not the Galilee,
Galatia? No. No maybe it means a what do you call it?
What's what was France? Gaul. Gaul. I was thinking Gaul. When I
went to Gaul, היו קורין לנדה גלמודה, hayu korin l'niddah galmuda, they
call a נדה niddah גלמודה. galmuda. מאי גלמודה? mai galmuda? What does
גלמודה galmuda mean? גמולה דא מבעלה, g'mula da m'ba'alah,
this woman is separated off, weaned away from her husband. Okay, גמרא
Gemara doesn't say what difference that makes, תוספות Tosfos says that it
helps explain a פסוק. Okay,
ואמר רבי עקיבא, v'amar Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, כשהלכתי
לאפריקי, k'she-halachti l'Afriki, when I went to Africa, fascinated where רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva went on all these trips. Okay, היו קורין למעה קשיטה.
hayu korin l'ma'ah kesitah. They call
a מעה ma'ah a certain coin a קשיטה. kesitah. למאי נפקא מינה,
l'mai nafka mina, why do I care? לפרושי מאה קשיטה, l'firushei me'ah
kesitah, to explain the verse of מאה קשיטה, me'ah kesitah, I know
it's דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, מאה דנקי. me'ah danki. That's in the תורה, Torah,
what does it mean? It means a hundred דנקי danki which is
a hundred מעה, ma'ah, I know what unit of coin we're talking
about. אמר רבי, now we're going to talk about רבי, כשהלכתי לכרכי
הים, k'she-halachti l'krachei hayam, when I went to the islands, היו קורין
למכירה כירה. hayu korin l'mechira kira. They would call selling כירה. kira.
למאי נפקא מינה, l'mai nafka mina, what difference does it make? לפרושי
l'firushei to explain the verse אשר כריתי לי asher karisi li that
I was כורה koreh for me which now we're going to say
means I purchased for me. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, amar Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish, and now we're moving from תנאים tannaim to אמוראים,
amoraim, כשהלכתי לתחום קן נשריא k'she-halachti l'tchum Kan Nishraya
wherever that is, היו קורין לכלה גינפי. hayu korin l'kallah ginfi. They
called a bride גינפי. ginfi. ולתרנגול u-letarnagol and they called a rooster
סיכוי. sichvi. לכלה גינפי מאי קרא, l'kallah ginfi mai kra, what's the
verse? יפה נוף משוש כל הארץ. y'feh nof mesos kol ha'aretz.
So the glory, you know, the beautiful foliage, not foliage, whatever, anyway,
what's Anyway, what do you call the things of the trees? I
guess the foliage but the whole crown, anyway, whatever it is. How
do they translate נוף? nof? נוף, Nof, what's it? Beautiful view. View?
Oh, no. Okay. Beautiful view, view the joy of the whole land.
So נוף nof and נינפי, ninfi, you know, כלה's kallah beautiful, so
that's כלה. kallah.
נינפי Ninfi is Greek according to them.
Ah, meaning what? A bride. Bride. Interesting. נינפי? Ninfi? Yeah. Interesting. Okay,
would that be anything at all like neophyte? נינפי, Ninfi, probably not.
Probably not. Okay. ולתרנגול שכוי. Ul'tarnagol sikhvi. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אי בעית אימא רבי יהושע בן לוי,
ei ba'it eima Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, מאי קרא? mai kra? What's
the verse? מי שת בטוחות חכמה או מי נתן לשכוי בינה? Mi
shat batuchot chochmah o mi natan la'sikhvi binah?
Who places in the בטוחות, batuchot, which are here read as the
kidneys, wisdom, and who gives to the שכוי sikhvi understanding? מי שת
בטוחות חכמה אלו כליות, Mi shat batuchot chochmah elu klayot, those are
the the kidneys which are where understanding in the ancient world to
be where wisdom and understanding came from. או מי נתן, O mi
natan, and if that sounds weird, you know, the heart is not
the seat of emotion, the heart is just a pump of blood,
but we associate the heart with emotion. So what organs of the
body metaphorically are associated with, you know, does not necessarily make sense.
So you know, so okay, kidneys is where your wisdom comes from.
That's a bit of a stretch but you get emotion.
Oh, maybe maybe you're right. Maybe that is why it's connected. Okay.
או מי נתן לשכוי בינה זה תרנגול. O mi natan la'sikhvi binah
zeh tarnagol.
So that's the rooster that knows when to crow in the morning.
Okay. לוי איקלע לההוא אתרא. Levi ikla le'hahu atra. Levi came to
a place. אתא גברא לקמיה ואמר ליה, Ata gavra lekamei ve'amar leih,
and whoever the place is doesn't matter and a person came and
said to him, כובן פלוני, kavan ploni, I was כובע kove'a a
certain person. So you know, I was כובע kove'a Joe Schmo. לא
הוי ידע מאי קאמר ליה. Lo hava yada mai ka'amar leih. He
didn't know what the guy was talking about. אזל שאל בי מדרשא.
Azal she'al be midrasha. So he went to the study hall. He
says I'll ask my colleagues, they'll tell me what this means. You
know I don't normally talk to the common people here. I don't
know what that what that word means. It's some vernacular. So anyway,
so אמרו ליה, amru leih, they said to him, גזלן אמר לך.
gazlan amar lach. He said I stole from somebody. דכתיב, as the
verse says, היקבע אדם אלהים כי אתם קבעים אתי ואמרתם במה קבענוך
המעשר והתרומה. Hayikba adam Elohim ki atem kove'im oti ve'amartem bameh kevanucha
hama'aser ve'hatrumah. That
you stole from me by not giving the מעשר. ma'aser. So קבען
kavan means to steal, which is interesting, it's based on a פסוק,
it's not just some vernacular. Why'd he not know it? Anyway, אמר
ליה רבה מברניש לרב אשי. amar leih Rava mi'Barnish le'Rav Ashi. So
Rava from Barnish said to Rav Ashi, אי הואי התם, ei havai
hatam, if that had happened to me, if somebody said this word
and I didn't know what he was talking about, הוה אמינא ליה,
hava amina leih, I would have said to him, back to the
guy who said this to me, I was כובע kove'a so and
so. I would have said to him, היכי קבעך? heichi kav'ach? How
did you כובע kove'a him? במאי קבעך? bemai kav'ach? With what were
you כובע kove'a him? ואמאי קבעך? ve'amai kav'ach? Why were you כובע
kove'a him? וממילא הוה ידענא. ve'mimmela hava yadana. But
based on his answer I would have figured it out by context.
Very smart. That's like me, I always forget people's names, so I
just start talking to them and I hope that eventually I'm going
to remember who they are, put them into some type of a
context. Oh, right, you're my cousin. No, okay, anyway. All right.
So I would have just started asking him questions and eventually I
would have figured it out. והוא סבר, Ve'hu savar, and he held,
מידי דאיסורא קאמר ליה. midei de'issura ka'amar leih. No, he was actually
telling him something about איסור. issur. Now he did tell him something
of איסור, issur, stole, but the גמרא Gemara means even something more
unsavory and he did not want to enter into a conversation about
finding out the details of this unsavory thing. So he just wanted
to end the conversation. Okay. Okay, now. לא
הוו ידעו רבנן, Lo havu yadu Rabbanan, the rabbis, here רבנן Rabbanan
means the rabbinic students, didn't know מאי סרוגין, mai serugin, what the
word סרוגין serugin meant, which appears in a משנה, Mishnah, which is
pretty funny because it's a pretty common word in Mishnaic Hebrew. שמעוה
לאמתא דבי רבי. Shamu'ah le'amta de'vei Rabbi.
So now basing on just the vernacular, they heard they heard the
maidservant in Rabbi's house. דחזיתנהו לרבנן דהוו עיילי פסקי פסקי. De'chazit'nhu le'Rabbanan
de'havu ayili piski piski. She would she would see the rabbis, the
students, coming in like groups and groups not all at one time.
ואמרה להו, Ve'amrah lehu, and she would say she said to them,
עד מתי אתם נכנסים סרוגין סרוגין? ad matay atem nichnasim serugin serugin?
How long are you going to be coming in סרוגין סרוגין? serugin
serugin? So they figured out it meant not to do something continuously,
but to do it in break it up in increments. Okay. אמר
להו, Amar lehu, so לא הוו ידעו רבנן, lo havu yadu Rabbanan,
the rabbis didn't know מאי חלוגלוגות. mai chaluglogot. What are חלוגלוגות, chaluglogot,
which are a certain type of a vegetable which are relevant for
certain issues about a זב zav and knowing whether he ate them
and so on and how to attribute the flow. יומא חד שמעוה
לאמתא דבי רבי. Yoma chad shamu'ah le'amta de'vei Rabbi. One day they
saw the maidservant in Rabbi's house. דחזייה לההוא גברא דהוה
מבדר פרפחיני. De'chazyah le'hahu gavra de'havah mevadar parpachinei. That she saw a
person that was scattering his פרפחיני, parpachinei, which is the purslane. Purslane.
There you go. אמרה ליה, Amrah leih, she said to him,
עד מתי אתה מפזר חלוגלוגך? ad matay atah mefazer chaluglogecha?
Okay.
So now they figured out what it was. לא הוו ידעו רבנן.
Lo havu yadu Rabbanan. This is just like me, you know, this
is why I'm always asking Charlie there like okay, so what does
שיינטופ Scheinthopf say? Because like how do I know what these words
mean, you know,
particularly,
you know, words that describe like nouns that describe the, you know,
there's like an infinite amount, not infinite, but obviously, you know, in
terms of the the different objects that we deal with in the
day that normally don't come up in like rabbinic discussion, right? I
mean, if you just think of all the different words we've got
to describe all these different objects. So whenever the Gemara starts talking
about like realia and using particular words, I have no idea what
it's talking about, you know. How frequently do you do you encounter
those words in in in legal texts? So here they are, they're
figuring it out by based on how the actual vernacular and how
it's used. Okay. לא הוו ידעי רבנן Lo havu yadei rabanan the
rabbis didn't know מה mai what it meant סלסלה ותרוממך. Salselah uteromemeka.
You will be מסלסל mesalsel it, understood to be the Torah, and
it will raise you up. So what's סלסלה? Salselah? יומא חד שמעוה
לאמתא דבי רבי Yoma chad sham'ua le'amta devei Rabbi once they saw
the maidservant of Rabbi's house, or they heard the maidservant of Rabbi's
house, דהוות אמרה ליה לההוא גברא dehavat amrah leih lehahu gavra she
would say to that man דהוה קמהפך בשעריה dehavah kamehapech besa'arei that
was always like playing with his hair, you know, and fiddling with
his hair and how beautiful his hair was and so on. Right,
the Rashi on Yosef. אמרה ליה עד מתי אתה מסלסל בשערך? Amrah
leih ad matai atah mesalsel besa'arecha? How long are you going to
be, you know, playing with your hair?
First of all, this maidservant must have had a doctorate in etymology.
No, but I I think the problem I think the problem more
is is that she just is closer to the, you know, you
know, to the people. I mean, and she's using the vernacular.
But also, they're thinking she's using a pure ancient form of the
Hebrew language.
A pure ancient form. So is that like what they taught them
in Rabbi's house? I guess that makes sense, you know, because I've
been saying it's a vernacular, but the vernacular would have been Palestinian
Aramaic. Right. And these words are Hebrew words. So that's actually a
good point. So what was why was the maidservant... Anyway, look, I
mean, maybe she was a very proper woman because she was always
trying to whip the rabbis in line, you know. They she was
the Miss Manners of the rabbis. Training the emanuensis? I don't think
so. So anyway, so she was the one that you're right, maybe
had this more, you know, this more this more ancient pure language
that she was connected to. Okay. לא הוו ידעי רבנן Lo havu
yadei rabanan the rabbis didn't know מה mai וטאטאתיה במטאטא השמד. Vetatatiha
bematate hashmad.
I will be מטטא metate it with the מטאטא metate of destruction.
So it's pretty clear or somewhat clear. So יומא חד שמעוה לאמתא
דבי רבי Yoma chad sham'ua le'amta devei Rabbi one day they heard
the maidservant of Rabbi say to her friend שקולי טאטיתא וטאטי ביתא
Shikuli tatita vetati beita
go grab your טאטי, tati, your טאטיתא tatita whatever, your מטאטא metate
and be מטטא metate your house. So clearly it meant a broom.
Okay, that's even in modern Hebrew, right? Isn't a broom מטאטא? metate?
Okay. So לא הוו ידעי רבנן
Lo
havu
yadei rabanan the rabbis didn't know מה mai השלך על ה' יהבך
Hashlech al Hashem yehavcha cast onto God your burden והוא יכלכלך vehu
yechalkeleka
and God will sustain you. So they didn't know what the word
יהבך yehavcha meant. So אמר רבה בר בר חנה Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chanah יומא חד הוה אזלינא בהדי ההוא טייעא Yoma chad havah
azlina bahadei hahu taya one day I was going with a certain
nomad, normally translated as Arab, והוה דרינא טונא Vehavah darina tuna and
I was carrying a load ואמר לי Ve'amar li and he said
to me שקול יהבך ושדי אגמלאי Shekol yehavcha ushdi agmalai
you know, take your load and throw it on my camel. So
you see יהב yehav means your load. Okay. I heard a beautiful
what do you call it?
story of the Dubner Maggid by this of השלך על ה' יהבך.
Hashlech al Hashem yehavcha. He says, you know, what does it mean?
He says that, you know, cast your burden to God. So he
says he says let me tell you I'll give you a you
know, let me tell you a משל. mashal. So here's a משל.
mashal. Best try. So this guy's going on the road and he's
carrying his really heavy
burden and and a wagon comes by and the wagon driver says
to him says, you know, get on my wagon, I'll give you
a ride into town. So he gets onto the wagon and he's
still carrying his his load on his back. So the wagon driver
looks at him, he says, what are you doing? Put your load
down, put it in the cart. You know, you're sitting in the
cart, why are you sitting with the load on the back? Take
the load off, put it in the cart. He says, dear Mr.
Wagon driver, you're already doing me such a kindness to carry me,
you know, to carry me into town. How could I ask you
also to carry my load? So he says this is what we
do. God supports the whole world, sustains the whole world, and we
feel we still have to carry our load. God, how could I
ask you to carry my load? He says he's already sustaining you,
so just give your load over to God. Very very beautiful little
משל. Yes.
Interesting to have תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים Amoraim using what would now
today be called academic methodology.
Right. Looking at yeah exploring how it's commonly used. Right. Okay, let's
now go to the next משנה. Mishnah. שופר של ראש השנה של
יעל פשוט. Shofar shel Rosh Hashanah shel yael pashut. And the שופר
shofar of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is of a יעל yael which
is a a mountain goat, right? Ibex. Ibex. Okay. What's an ibex
exactly?
In the picture it says like a goat with big horns that
go crazy.
Yeah, so somewhat like a mountain goat.
Yeah, it's a form it's a goat.
Okay, fine. Okay, also a good Okay, also a good Scrabble word.
Okay. So, so it's straight, meaning it's not twisted, you know, it's
got a curve, but it's not totally like twisted. Okay. ופיו מצופה
זהב u'piv metzupeh zahav and its mouth would be coated, would be
plated in gold. Now, this is only in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. We're going to see that we're describing what it would be
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ושתי חצוצרות מן הצדדים. u'shtei chatzotzrot
min hatzedadim. And again, clearly we're not talking about your normal blowing
of the שופר. shofar There would be two trumpets on the side
on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah when they blow the שופר shofar. in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
And that one was a gold, by the way.
Exactly. Exactly. So much for not using the gold.
Right. A good, excellent point. Okay. שופר מאריך וחצוצרות מקצרות. shofar maarich
v'chatzotzrot m'katzrot. So they would all be playing, but the חצוצרות chatzotzrot
would go short and the שופר shofar sound would continue longer. So
you hear the שופר sound by itself and also it emphasizes what's
the focus. שמצות היום בשופר, she'mitzvat hayom bashofar, the primary מצוה mitzvah
of the day is the שופר. The חצוצרות chatzotzrot are only an
accompaniment. ובתעניות. u'v'ta'aniyot. Now, on fast days, because on fast days they
would make twice... they would do a שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei with
twenty-four ברכות. brachos. They would add six ברכות brachos unique to the
fast day, and when they would say those six ברכות brachos in
the repetition of the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, at the end of
each ברכה, bracha, they would do a... they would blow the שופרות
shofrot and חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. And they would say הריעו בני אהרן הריעו,
hariu b'nei Aharon hariu, you know, תקעו בני אהרן תקעו, tiku b'nei
Aharon tiku, and then the כהנים, kohanim, at least in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, would blow the שופר, blow the חצוצרות chatzotzrot at
the end of each of these additional ברכות brachos that they made
in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei on the fast days. So and that
time when they did that, those in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
by the way, blowing the שופר and חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, and even outside
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they would blow שופר and חצוצרות chatzotzrot
on fast days in the... you know, in all over. So it's
that is an interesting thing to think about of the integration of
the blowing of a שופר with שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei with a
day that's particularly about reaching out to God and prayer, how we
take that model by ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and we basically employ
that, the idea of using it. Now you could say it's not
a ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. model. It's the פסוקים. psukim Right, the
פסוקים says, you know, you know, it says what's it? כי תבואו
מלחמה בארצכם על הצר הצרר אתכם והרעתם בחצוצרות. ki tavo'u milchama b'artzechem
al hatzar hatzorer etchem v'hareiotem bachatzotzrot. Right, you blow the חצוצרות chatzotzrot
as a way of calling out to God. So that's already, and
that's, you know, and you do it on the קרבנות korbanot and
then תפילה tefillah replaces קרבנות. korbanot. So the whole idea of the
חצוצרות chatzotzrot as calling out to God is something that way played
a central role in the תפילות tefillot of תענית. ta'anit. And there
the emphasis was חצוצרות chatzotzrot because that's the פסוקים in the Torah.
But it's an important parallel with ראש
השנה.
Rosh
Hashanah
A תענית ta'anit for rain.
For rain. A תענית ta'anit for rain. Right, not our historical תעניות.
ta'aniyot. These are the תענית ta'anit for rain. Okay. ובתעניות בששל זכרים
כפופים. u'v'ta'aniyot beshel zecharim kfufim. Now the שופרות Shofros. they would use
would be rams' horns which would be twisted, you know, like the
whole big, you know, fancy long twisted horns. ופיהן מצופה כסף u'pihen
metzupeh kasef and it would be covered with silver the mouth. ושתי
חצוצרות באמצע u'shtei chatzotzrot ba'emtza and the and the trumpets would be
in the middle, right? And presumably שופר מקצר וחצוצרות מאריכות. shofar m'katzer
v'chatzotzrot maarichot. The שופר would be shorter and the חצוצרות chatzotzrot would
go longer. So there the חצוצרות chatzotzrot are the focus, they're in
the center, they go longer, and the שופר is just the accompaniment.
שמצות היום בחצוצרות she'mitzvat hayom bachatzotzrot on a תענית, ta'anit, the מצוה
would be חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. That would be in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash they would still do
blowings but they would not be with in the middle and on
the sides and covered with silver. This whole thing about this whole
collection of instruments was only in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay.
Now relatedly שווה היובל לראש השנה. shavah hayovel l'Rosh Hashanah. יובל, Yovel
the Jubilee year where you also blow a שופר, similar to ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah לתקיעה ולברכה. litkiah u'livrachah. For for the תקיעות tkiyot
and for the ברכות, brachos, like you know how many תקיעות tkiyot
you do and the various ברכות brachos like you know מלכויות זכרונות
ושופרות. Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot. רבי יהודה אומר בראש השנה תוקעים בששל זכרים
וביובל בשל יעלים. Rabbi Yehudah omer b'Rosh Hashanah tokiyim beshel zecharim u'v'yovel
beshel yeilim. There is a difference in terms of the nature of
the horn that you use. On ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah you use
rams, so notice he's already arguing on the first part of the
משנה mishna that says you use יעל. ya'el. Here he says you
use a ram's horn on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah וביובלות בשל יעלים
u'v'yovlot beshel yeilim and on the יובל Yovel that you use the
the ibex horn. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah basically argues A we're
not... יובל Yovel and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. are not the same
for the type of horn and B he argues what horn they
would use on
ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah זכרים zecharim means rams.
Yes. זכרים zecharim is rams, yes. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי לוי amar Rabbi Levi מצוה של ראש
השנה ושל יום הכפורים בכפופים. mitzvah shel Rosh Hashanah v'shel Yom Kippurim
bichfufim.
Okay? ושל כל השנה בפשוטים. v'shel kol hashanah bifshutim. On ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah, and יום הכפורים Yom Kippurim you use bent horns, right,
and the rest of the year you use, meaning on תעניות, ta'aniyot,
you use straight horns. So this is getting a little confusing who
says what. Okay, so here you have ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah יובל,
Yovel. and
תענית. ta'anit. Okay, three times. Okay. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said said
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was was יעל, ya'el, פשוט. pashut. Okay, יעל
ya'el is always פשוט. pashut. Okay, יובל Yovel, presumably the same. and
תעניות Ta'aniot was איל Ayal or זכרים Zecharim and therefore כפופים. Kefufim.
Okay, that's תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. But יהודה, Yehudah, we don't know
says that here you would
do איל, Ayal, you would do כפוף, Kafuf,
you would do the and on יובל Yovel you would do, you
would do יעל. Yael. So number one is he doesn't have it
as the same, he has a difference between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
and יעל, Yael, and number two he has ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
itself being different. And now in the גמרא Gemara we have
לוי, Levi, right, who says ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah would be איל
Ayal or זכרים, Zecharim, you know if you want the language of
the גמרא, Gemara which is כפוף Kafuf
and on יובל Yovel it would be איל Ayal כפופים Kfufim
and only on תענית Ta'anit would it be יעל Yael and therefore
פשוט. Pashut. So you can figure out the other possible configurations but
you see all the differences here, right? He's like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that he's got it bent, but he's not like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda because he's got the same thing for ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah? and יובל. Yovel, Okay, but he's also not like תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma has יעל Yael for both, he's
got the איל, Ayal, he's got זכרים Zecharim for both, okay, and
he's also not like anybody in terms of the תענית. Ta'anit. Here
you've got כפופים, Kfufim, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda didn't have a stay
to say about the כפופים, Kfufim, right, and he says it's פשוט.
Pashut. So everybody's all over the map, okay, in terms of what
it is. So the גמרא Gemara is going to try to make
some sense of at least what might be informing these different opinions.
Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. והתנן שופרו של ראש השנה של יעל פשוט, v'ha tnan shofaro
shel Rosh Hashanah shel Yael Pashut, doesn't the משנה Mishnah say it's
straight on ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? How could he say it's bent
on
ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah. הוא דאמר כהאי תנא דתניא, Hu d'amar k'hai
tanna d'tanya, he says like the following תנא, Tanna, like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda already in the משנה Mishnah
says זכרים, Zecharim, and זכרים Zecharim presumably means
כפופים. Kfufim. הוא דאמר כהאי תנא דתניא דתניא רבי יהודה אומר בראש
השנה יוצאים בשל זכרים כפופים וביובל בשל יעלים. Hu d'amar k'hai tanna
d'tanya d'tanya Rabbi Yehuda omer b'Rosh Hashanah yotzim b'shel Zecharim Kfufim u'v'Yovel
b'shel Yeilim. So just simply the משנה, Mishnah, the only reason they
quoted the ברייתא Braita was because in the ברייתא Braita it's explicit
that זכרים Zecharim means כפופים. Kfufim. Okay, so he's like at least
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that he uses כפוף Kafuf on ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. They disagree on יובל, Yovel but at least he
has רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of כפוף Kafuf on ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah Okay, so the גמרא says like this. ולימא הלכתא כרבי יהודה,
v'leima hilchta k'Rabbi Yehuda,
just tell me we rule like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. No. אי אמרת הלכתא כרבי יהודה, Ee amart
hilchta k'Rabbi Yehuda, had he said that, הוי אמינא אפילו של יובל
נמי כרבי יהודה, havi amina afilu shel Yovel nami k'Rabbi Yehuda, you
would have thought he agrees with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that יובל
Yovel also
is a, is a what do you call it, is a twisted
horn, a straight horn. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that יובל
Yovel is a straight horn. You would have thought he agrees with
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda there. So,
wait a minute, הלכתא הוי אמינא אפילו של יובל נמי כרבי יהודה
סבירא ליה, hilchta havi amina afilu shel Yovel nami k'Rabbi Yehuda s'vira
lei, קא משמע לן kamashma lan that he doesn't, he agrees that
it's twisted, but as opposed to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that makes
a difference between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יובל, Yovel he keeps
with the idea that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יובל Yovel are
the same. Okay, so basically the, you know, there's two issues here.
One issue is that do you basically feel that ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and יובל Yovel, have to be the same, where לוי Levi
and תנא קמא Tanna Kamma feel that and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
does not. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is willing to deal with each
thing separately. By the way, I want to say an interesting point
if we had more time we'd look inside in the משנה Mishnah
in תענית Ta'anit that discusses the blowing of the שופר on תעניות
Ta'aniot or the חצוצרות Chatzotrot as we spoke about. And there when
it speaks about the ברכות Brachos that you make, the six extra
ברכות Brachos you make in the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says you know what two of those six ברכות
Brachos are?
זכרונות Zichronos and שופרות. Shofros. Not מלכויות Malchuyos because מלכויות Malchuyos isn't
relevant. But at least זכרונות Zichronos and שופרות. Shofros And רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה Mishnah says you don't do זכרונות Zichronos
and שופרות on תענית. Taanis. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't have
this idea of just like let's just equate things one another, everything
is distinct, everything has its distinct character. So one issue here is
that is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. like יובל Yovel, or not? Okay,
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and לוי Levi says
yes and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no. The other issue is
about
whether you're using פשוט Pashut or כפוף. Kafuf. Okay, it's all right.
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says פשוט Pashut and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
here says, we'll do it like that, כפוף. Kafuf. Okay, so you
know, it's, so לוי Levi is having like a split פסק. psak.
I like רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda idea of כפוף, Kafuf, but I
don't like his idea of יובל being different from ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah יובל is the same for ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah so they're
both going to be כפופים. Kfufim.
And visually now it's very easy to read.
I know, I thought so. Thank you. So, but it's okay, you've
got the colors and the twisted things. It's all right. Let's just
finish up at least this part, the end of the דף. daf.
So the גמרא says like this. במאי קמיפלגי, B'mai kamifligi, what's the
debate about? I'm sorry,
yeah, what's the debate about? Now forget לוי Levi for a minute.
What's the debate in the משנה Mishnah about whether on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah. you want a straight one or you want a twisted
one? So the גמרא says like
this. במאי קמיפלגי, B'mai kamifligi, מר סבר בראש השנה כמה דכייף איניש.
mar savar b'Rosh Hashanah kama d'kaif inish. דעתיה טפי מעלי. dateih tfei
ma'alei. So now it's very important, now we're turning to the questions
of symbolism and an approach towards ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah One holds
on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. your דעת, da'at, your intent, your focus
should be straight. You know, you're thinking about just going straight to
God, bringing your prayers straight to God. You want something straight to
symbolize that. וביום הכיפורים— u-ve-Yom ha-Kippurim
I'm sorry, did I get that wrong? Yeah, I was jumping ahead
to the next opinion, excuse me. כמה דכייף איניש דעתיה טפי מעלי.
kama de-khayif inish dateih tfei ma'alei. The more your דעת da'at is
bent over, meaning it should be about you're about more like supplication
or more like a sense of like being down on yourself, you
know, focusing on on all the תשובה teshuvah that you have to
do, feeling your sense of shame, there's a sense of being sort
of bent over, supplicating, negating yourself. That's an approach to ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah וביום הכיפורים כמה דפשיט איניש דעתיה טפי מעלי. u-ve-Yom ha-Kippurim
kama de-pashit inish dateih tfei ma'alei. Yom Kippur it's more going straight.
Now what does that mean going straight? So רש"י Rashi, says because
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, on יובל, it's about announcing freedom, right?
So announce freedom, you don't have a sense of twisted, you want
sort of a sense, you know, you want to burst it forth
and it's straight and it's direct and a straight line, you know,
and it's just making that announcement getting it out there. Okay, so
that's the idea of here it's bent and here it's straight. He
doesn't buy in that it has to be the same and there's
a logic for it to be different. You want the announcement to
go straight out, you want yourself to be bent over. That's רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And what does the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma hold?
ומר סבר, u-mar savar,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds, בראש השנה כמה דפשיט איניש דעתיה
טפי מעלי. be-Rosh Hashanah kama de-pashit inish dateih tfei ma'alei. No, on
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, you should be like going straight to God.
Don't focus on beating yourself up and on sort of self-abnegation and
and you know and prostration, no, focus on you know getting close
to God. ובתעניות u-ve-ta'aniyot there's a difference, right? Is it about guilt
and sin or is it about drawing close? ובתעניות כמה דכייף איניש
דעתיה טפי מעלי. u-ve-ta'aniyot kama de-khayif inish dateih tfei ma'alei. So bracketing
here the question about יובל, right? On תענית ta'anit at least you're
going to want you're going I'm sorry, here on תענית ta'anit that's
when you're going to want to be bent over. תענית ta'anit it's
about oh we're terrible, we sinned, ashes on the head, you know,
so that's about focusing on the sin. ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. interesting,
is not so much about focusing on sin and the negation and
you're terrible, but it's focusing on getting close to God. Very different
way of thinking about ראש השנה. Before we end I want to
say another thing that connects to this that the גמרא is ignoring
because the גמרא is focusing on twisted versus straight, but also twisted
is a ram. And a ram is about, right, is about like
the עקידה. Akeidah. So the עקידה Akeidah also, what's the עקידה Akeidah
in its race? It's about self-sacrifice. It's about, you know, it's about
sort of frustration, giving yourself up. It's a different type of an
imagery as opposed to like if you think about the proud mountain
goat there, you know, whatever. So even the animal views are very
different and evoke that imagery in a different way. And one final
important point is, it ties into an issue we've raised before of
is the שופר directed to you or is the שופר directed to
God? If you think about the שופר as a call to do
תשובה, teshuvah, that is very much the bent over and you hear
it and you're fearful and you know and you're reflective, that's the
שופר this רש"י, Rashi if you read רש"י Rashi closely, רש"י is
saying this. That's the שופר that you're hearing. But if you think
of the שופר as part of our prayers and as the way
of bringing our prayers to God, so bringing your prayers to God
is not a twisted direction. Bringing your prayers to God is like
the straight, you know, the straight line to God. So there's a
lot of very interesting things in the symbolism here, how the symbolisms
match the shape, match the animal, and also what those say about
whether שופר is directed to you or is it directed to God.
תוספות Tosafot has a long discussion about how do we פוסקין, poskin,
you know, and תוספות Tosafot actually says this is presumably this is
only לכתחילה, lechatchila, it's only a symbolic question, it's not a real
הלכה halacha issue. But תוספות Tosafot at the end says, no, maybe
it's actually הלכה למעשה halacha le-ma'aseh and it's מעכב me'akeiv and if
you don't have the right one you're really not יצא, yotzei, okay,
which is like hard to believe. We certainly don't פוסקין poskin that
way because as תוספות Tosafot says, the first משנה Mishnah says everything
is כשר kasher for a שופר. So the general assumption here is
this is just a symbolic לכתחילה lechatchila question, but nevertheless a real
important thing at the heart of how do we think about what
שופר is all about. And with that—